<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Golden letany in Englysshe</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15707.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23859249</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23859249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1836:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Golden letany in Englysshe</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted at London in Fauster Lane, by me Iohn Skot dwellynge in Saynt Leonardes parysshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1536?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [a]-b⁸ c⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Litanies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26916:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26916:1"/>
            <p>The golden Letany in Englyſſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Father on throne, Christ crucified, Holy Spirit as dove</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="litany">
            <pb facs="tcp:26916:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. Chryſte haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Lorde haue mercy vpon vs: and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vs vertue of ſoule &amp; mynde in erth and aboue erth / that we may ſerue the after the pleaſure of thy wyll. God euerlaſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; father by your heuenly vertue haue mercy vpon vs. The ſonne of god redemer of the world / haue mercy vpon vs. The holy gooſt by thy goodnes / haue
<pb facs="tcp:26916:2"/> mercy vpon vs. God by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create &amp; vndeuyded trinite haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy diuyne &amp; vne eſſence / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne nature / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy infinyte mekenes haue mercy vpon vs. By thy ſelfe &amp; all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that in the thou behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt / haue mercy vpon vs. By the creacyon of heuen &amp; erthe / &amp; all thynges that in them are / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy goodnes that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> createſt aungels / haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy
<pb facs="tcp:26916:3"/> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the loue that thou haddeſt wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted man to thyne owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, haue mercy vpon vs. By the greate loue that thou had to redeme man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By that ineffable loue that thou hadde whan thou chaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy virgyn Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye to be thy mother, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By Maryes holy name, that deſcended fro the hye trone of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite &amp; efflowed haue mercy vpon vs. By the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cepcion
<pb facs="tcp:26916:3"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgyn thy mother the whiche was ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified in her mothers wombe, haue thou mercy vpon vs. By the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly natiuite of her / haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. By the perfyte purite and the mekenes of her / haue mercy vpon vs. By the mooſt humble affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion whiche ſhe toke of the in thy lap of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father in her virgyn wombe / haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. By the meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy hye maieſtie that thou dayned not to deſcend in to the wombe of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn
<pb facs="tcp:26916:4"/> mary haue mercy vpon vs. By the frayle nature of ours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it pleſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to take for our ſynne / not abhorrynge haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy holy natiuite that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldeſt voucheſaue to be borne of a mayde / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the ineffable ioye which thy mother had in thy byrth haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the colde crybbe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vyle clothes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and put / &amp; nouryſſhed with mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mylke / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ioye of the
<pb facs="tcp:26916:4"/> ſhepeherdes whiche honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the in the crybbe / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion of ſhedynge of thy precyous bloode / and by thy holy name Iheſus / and by all thy holy ſayntes / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the oblacyon and prayer of the thre kynges / haue mercye vpon vs. By the oblacyon that thou were offered in to the temple / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy flyenge in to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypte / &amp; by all the neceſſitie that thou ſuffred there with
<pb facs="tcp:26916:5"/> the virgyn thy mother / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By thy goynge agayne fro Egypte in to Nazareth &amp; obedience that thou were vnder thy pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rentes, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy humble &amp; meke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſacion that thou had on erth the tyme of .xxxiij. yere thou were conuerſaunt / ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By thy meke obedyence &amp; paynes haue mercy vpon vs. By thy holy meditacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and worke / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy baptyſme
<pb facs="tcp:26916:5"/> and appering of the holy tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy holy ſtedfaſt contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>placyons &amp; knelynges, and ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of the fendes temptacion in deſerte, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy thurſt and hungre, colde &amp; heate whiche in this vale of myſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thou ſuffred / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ſorowe of thy herte / labour and wery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy great pouertye and contemplacion / haue mercy vpon vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obtrectacion
<pb facs="tcp:26916:6"/> that thyne enmyes detracte to the / haue mercy vpon vs By thy watchynges &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy holſome doctryne &amp; benefytes and ſtrengthe of reſyſtynge / that thou grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to thyne enemyes / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the tokens / wonders / and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that thou dyd / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy meke ſwete and holy conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy holy teares and thy meke entrynge in to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem
<pb facs="tcp:26916:6"/> on palme ſonday / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By the ſhrewde counſell in whome the peruerted iewes conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the vnto the deth / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed deſyre that thou had to redeme vs / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy meke waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of thy diſciples fete and Iudas the traytoure / haue mercy vpon vs. By the mooſt beloued inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of thy worthy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy blyſſed body &amp; bloode lorde haue mercy vpon vs.
<pb facs="tcp:26916:7"/> By the profounde loue that thou ſouffered thy diſcyple Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſt on thy breſt at thy laſt ſupper / haue mercy vpon vs. By the peace that thou gaue to thy diſcyples / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy holy wordes and ſermons haue mercy vpon vs. By thy hugely great heuyneſſe that thou hadde whan thou prayed to thy father in the yarde nye the mount of oly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uete / haue mercy vpon vs. By the vertue of thy prayer that thou ſhedde out .iij. ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,
<pb facs="tcp:26916:7"/> haue mercy vpon vs. By thy paynefull &amp; fearfull deth, haue mercy vpon vs. By the agony that thou offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red thy ſelfe wylfully to the deth, in obeyinge thy father haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the ſhedynge of thy bloode for anguyſſh, haue mercy vpon vs. By the mekeneſſe that thou wolde be conforted of the aungell, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort me in all tymes, &amp; haue mercy vpon vs. By the triumphant wyl that thou had whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> went to mete theym that ſought
<pb facs="tcp:26916:8"/> the in to dethe / haue mercy vpon vs. By the fearfull ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng &amp; the violent layenge on handes of the iewes / ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By thy immutable goodnes that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> refuſed not to take the kyſſe of Iudas the traytour / and that thou healed the eare of the byſſhops ſeruaunt / that was ſtriken of / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy holy bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the which thou were taken ledde and braydes in which thou were made we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that nyght / haue mercy
<pb facs="tcp:26916:8"/> vpon vs. By the buffet whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſuffredeſt on the ſeate of Annas the byſſhop and other vnknowynge the / ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By the loue and charite that thou haddeſt whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were ledde bounden before the byſſhop Cayfas / haue mercy vpon vs. By the falſe wytneſſe &amp; lyes and vniuſtly dampned haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the vyle ſpyttynges and illuſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy buffettes and ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / haue mercy vpon vs.
<pb facs="tcp:26916:9"/> By the blynde felyng of thy holy eyen / and other repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues that thou ſuffered that nyght, haue mercy vpon vs By thy gracious beholdyng that thou beheldeſt Peter, &amp; by all that labour and ſecret vnknowen turme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whiche thou ſuffered at that nyght haue mercy vpon vs. By thy preſentacyon and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion whiche they brought agaynſte the before Pylate the Iudge, haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. By the deſpyſynge and illuſyon that thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb facs="tcp:26916:9"/> before Herode / &amp; the whyte veſture in the which he ſente the to Pilate / haue mercy vpon vs. By all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmacyon and vnknowen labour that thou ſuffered in goynge from one iudge to an other / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy great pacience &amp; ſtylneſſe / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ſhamefull pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of thy clothes &amp; harde byndyng of thy body to the pyller / haue mercy vpon vs</p>
            <p>By the harde beatynge of ſcourges / haue mercy vpon
<pb facs="tcp:26916:10"/> vs. By the innumerable woundes of thy precious bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy hugely ſhedde out, haue mercy vpon vs. By all thy paynes, dolours, colde and ſhakyng, and the glad thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng out of thy bloode / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By the purpull veſtement and the crowne of thorne thruſted to thy blyſſed heed with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, haue mercy vpon vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innumerable paynes that thou were turmented whan they ſmote the crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of thorne with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges
<pb facs="tcp:26916:10"/> ſeptre / and by the great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of thy precyous blode haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the ſcornefull honourynge and ſalutyng of the iewes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſayde: Hayle kynge of iewes / haue mercy vpon vs By theyr vyle ſpyttynge in thy dyuyne face togyther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> harde ſtrokes / haue mercy vpon vs. By all the paynes and heuyneſſe of herte that thou had wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate ledde the out vnto the people bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the crowne of thorne and the purpull veſtement
<pb facs="tcp:26916:11"/> and ſayd, behold man / haue mercy vpon vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſentence of deth &amp; vyle name / ledyng the vnto the mounte of Caluarye / haue mercy vpon vs. By the loue that thou bare the croſſe to the place of payne vpon thy backe, haue mercy vpon vs. By the labour / anguyſſhe / ſhame and beatyng whiche thou ſuffredeſt by the waye haue mercy vpon vs. By al thy harde ſteppes that thou had bearyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe whan thou went to thy deth / haue
<pb facs="tcp:26916:11"/> mercy vpon vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great heuynes of thy ſholders in whiche thou bare the croſſe vnto the tyme thou fayled for weykenes / haue mercy vpon vs. By the compaſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy herte that thou had in metynge of thy ſorowful mother in bearynge of thy croſſe haue mercy vpon vs. By thy heuy lokyng &amp; aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge vp the hye mount of Caluarye / on whiche thou were crucifyed / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ſpoylynge of thy clothes in mooſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:26916:12"/> in the eye ſyght of the virgyn thy mother &amp; all the people, haue mercy vpon vs By the ſeynge that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were naked, full of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and laden with greate ſorowes with the colde of the wynde ſufferyng tyll the croſſe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re made redy, haue mercy vpon vs. By thy heuy ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes whan thou wenteſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to the croſſe, and theron faſtened with boyſtous nay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, haue mercy vpon vs. By ekynge thy payne &amp; thy wepynge, haue mercy vpon
<pb facs="tcp:26916:12"/> vs. By the ache of thy vey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſynewes &amp; all thy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres on thy croſſe, haue mercy vpon vs. By the thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of thy ryght hande, &amp; ſhedynge of thy precyous bloode, lorde make vs clene from all ſynne, &amp; haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. By the thyrling of thy lyft hande, and by the holy wounde of the ſame &amp; thy holy bloode ſaue vs and haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the ſore dryuynge of the nayles and by thy holy fete, and by the woundes of the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:26916:13"/> and by the precyous bloode from the ſheding / purge vs &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyle vs to thy father &amp; haue mercy on vs. By the lyftynge vp of thy mooſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly body on the croſſe / and by the violent paynes of it all thy holy membres were ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully payned haue mercy on vs. By the heuyneſſe of thy herte &amp; all the ſtrengthes of thy ſoule / ſaue me / defende me / and haue mercy on vs. By the diuiſion or partyng of thy veſture / and the lotte whiche they caſt on thy cote
<pb facs="tcp:26916:13"/> without ſeme / thou ſeynge it / haue mercy vpon vs. By the loue that thou hynge .iij houres on the croſſe alyue / haue mercy on vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preues and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyon full of wordes that thou herde han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpon vs. By the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynges &amp; ſorowes &amp; confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons that thou ſuffred han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on vs. By al the dolours that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſuffred in thy rybbes hyppes and ſholders crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed / haue mercy vpon vs.
<pb facs="tcp:26916:14"/> By all the paynes that thou had ſpredde on the croſſe in thy ſynewes, veynes, fete, and all thy membres, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By thy great mekeneſſe that thou prayed to thy father for thyne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, haue mercy vpon vs. By thy mercy that thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thefe paradyſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mercy vpon vs. By the charge that thou had to thy mother in thy turme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending her to thy beloued diſciple, haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</p>
            <p>By the ſwerde of ſorowe
<pb facs="tcp:26916:14"/> that went vnto thy moders herte, and the compaſſyon &amp; teares that ſhe ſhed out for ſorowe ſtandyng vnder the croſſe, haue mercy vpon vs. By al thy holy teares on the croſſe and al the tyme of thy lyfe ſhedde out, haue mercy vpon vs. By thy thyrſt / gall and eyſell with vyneygre, gyue me to taſte of thy ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſpiryte, &amp; haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By all thy holy wordes by the pronounced vpon the croſſe / and all thoſe that in thy lyfe thou ſhewed, haue
<pb facs="tcp:26916:15"/> mercy vpon vs. By the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng &amp; crye in the whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended thy ſpiryte to thy father, our ſoules may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mended to the / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ſeparacion of thy holy ſoule from thy blyſſed &amp; diuyne body / hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercy vpon vs. By the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clynynge of thy holy heade vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy breſt / enclyne ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Ieſus vnto vs and haue mercy vpon vs. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy deth and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bruſynges in whiche thy herte was broken / haue
<pb facs="tcp:26916:15"/> mercy vpon vs. By the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of thy ſyde &amp; the reed wounde of it and the precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blode good lorde thyrle our herte with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpere of all thy loue &amp; haue mercy vpon vs. By the precyous bloode and water that ranne out of thy holy hert / waſſhe and make vs clene in the ſame holy water &amp; blode from all our ſynnes / &amp; haue mercy vpon vs. By the mercy that thou ſhewed on the croſſe to Centurio / and all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that euer thou ſhewed to
<pb facs="tcp:26916:16"/> man / haue mercy vpon vs. By the deſcendynge of thy holy ſoule to limbo patrum / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the vertue of thy holy ſoule that thou brakeſt vp the gates of hell, and delyuered out the ſoules of thy frendes / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng downe of thy holy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the croſſe / and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne ſepulture of it, &amp; the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng of the virgyn thy mother, &amp; Mary magdalen &amp; other of thy frendes, haue mercy vpon vs. By all the
<pb facs="tcp:26916:16"/> labour / weryneſſe / ſorowe and heuyneſſe that thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred from tke day of thy Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuite vnto the houre of the departynge of thy ſoule fro thy body / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy gloryous &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in body &amp; ſoule / haue mercy vpon vs. By the ineffable ioye of thy mother &amp; other of thy fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / and the glory of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / haue mercy vpon vs. By the grace that thou apperedeſt to Mary magda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leyn and other women and
<pb facs="tcp:26916:17"/> to thy diſcyple in thy impaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble body after thy reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction / haue mercy vpon vs. By thy meruaylous &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous aſcencyon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte vs lorde in all our nedes / and haue mercy vpon vs. By the diuyne conſolacion and ſendynge of the holy gooſt in to thy diſcyples / glad vs / ſanctifye vs / ſtrength vs in fayth hope and charite / and haue mercy vpon vs. By thy gloryous &amp; dyuyne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie &amp; the vertue of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name kepe vs / gouerne
<pb facs="tcp:26916:17"/> vs now &amp; euerlaſtyng / and haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the ſonne in thy holy godhed to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther in thy manhode hyd haue mercy on vs. By the ioye that thy ſelfe were in / haue mercy on vs. By thy ſelfe &amp; all goodnes &amp; meryte that in the &amp; in thy mother thou beholdeſt / haue mercy vpon vs. By the myniſters Mychael and Gabryell, ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers deputed to me, and all other thy celeſtiall ſpirites / haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. By the interceſſion and merites of
<pb facs="tcp:26916:18"/> ſaynt Peter &amp; Paule, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euangeliſt, and other of thyne apoſtels / haue mercy vpon vs. By the merytes &amp; interceſſion of thy holy mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs Laure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; Stephen, &amp; all other / haue mercy vpon vs. By the vertues and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of the holy fathers &amp; confeſſours Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cis, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyne, Anthony, &amp; all other, haue mercy on vs. By the merytes and prayers of the holy ſaynt Anne, Katheryn Barbara, and all other holy virgyns &amp; holy wydowes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26916:18"/> chaſte women / haue mercy on vs. By the merytes and prayers of al thy holy choſen ſayntes, that are, were and are for to come in heuen &amp; in erth / haue mercy on vs. Succour vs ſwete Ieſu in the tremblynge and ſtrayte day of iudgement, &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vs in this exile &amp; tranſytory lyfe thoſe thynges that be neceſſary to the helth of our body &amp; ſoule / and after this lyfe to lyue in ioye with the euerlaſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly withouten en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Amen. Lord heare gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly
<pb facs="tcp:26916:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> my prayers, and that my crye may come to the. &amp;c praye we. Lorde gyue to the quycke grace / to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in eſpecyall for them that I am bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den N. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche holyneſſe, peace &amp; concorde. And that thou wylt voucht ſaue to take this prayer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour and glory of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, and that thou wylt vouche ſaue to haue mercy vpon vs. And to redeme vs by thy paynfull deth / and to forgyue vs all our ſynnes / and graunte euerlaſtyngly
<pb facs="tcp:26916:19"/> that we may perceuer in all goodnes / and that we may ſerue the. And after this lyf we may deſerue to reygne with the in euerlaſtyng glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye and lyfe without ende.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A deuoute blyſſynge in englyſſhe, lately tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated out of frenſſhe by Robert Copland.</head>
            <p>THe holy croſſe be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me / the blyſſyng of god be vpon me, with the blyſſynge that god blyſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges which Herode
<pb facs="tcp:26916:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo that none enemyes haue power to greue nor to vexe me from all good werkes / the whiche graunt the hole Trinite, father, ſonne and holy gooſt. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>¶ Laus deo.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London in Fauſter lane, by me Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Skot, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in ſaynt Leonardes paryſſhe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26916:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
